Finding Aid for Center for the Education of Women (University of Michigan) Records, 1919-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Central Office Files 1961-1998
  - Topical Files
    - 1962-1998
      - Women in Science
        - Programs
          - Internships
            - High School ("Summer Internships in the Sciences for High School Women") 1985-1991, 5 folders (Box 17)
              (folder for 1989 also includes information on "Summerscience for Girls", aimed at 8th graders)
            - Undergraduate Internships for Winter Term 1990
              - Planning 1989-1990 (Box 17)
              - Project Summary Booklet April 1990 (Box 17)
              - Regents' Meeting Presentation September 1990 (Box 17)
          - Science Day on Campus (Box 18)
            - Programs for High Schools and Middle Schools 1988, 3 folders (Box 18)
            - Proposed Science/Technology Day 1989 (Box 18)
          - Traditional Students
            - Discussion Group Materials November 1988-February 1989 (Box 18)
            - Michigan Association of Women Dental Students, Fall 1989 (Box 18)
            - Planning 1988-1989 (Box 18)
        - Research Surveys
          - General/Miscellaneous
            - Marian S. Parker Scholars (Engineering Pipeline Project) undated (Box 18)
            - Summerscience for Girls (Evaluation and Research Proposal) undated (Box 18)
            - Undergraduate Women and Science (Intern Survey) January 1990, undated (Box 18)
            - University of Arizona Project (Jean Manis Correspondence) 1993-1995 (Box 18)
            - University of Michigan Project on the Undergraduate Experience in Science and Engineering 1994 (Box 18)
            - WIS Survey Instruments 1987-1995, undated (Box 18)
            - Women's Studies 312 (Barbara Sloat), "Gender and Science", Fall 1989 (Box 18)
          - Housing Survey
            - Comments on Responses October 1992 (Box 18)
            - Completed Questionnaires, ca Fall 1992
              - 1: Engineering (Box 18)
              - 2: Mathematics (Box 18)
              - 3: Physical and Natural Sciences (Box 18)
              - 4: Biomedical Sciences (Box 18)
              - 5: Social Sciences (Box 18)
              - 6: Humanities (Box 18)
              - 8: Business (Box 18)
              - 9: Undecided/NA (Box 18)
              - Uncoded (Box 18)
            - Data Analysis undated (Box 18)
            - Letter and Questionnaire August 1992 (Box 18)
          - Science for Life
            - Applicant Questionnaires undated (Box 18)
              (probably either 1992 or 1994)
            - Coding 1992-1994 (Box 18)
            - Evaluation 1993 (Box 18)
            - Proposal, ca 1991 (Box 18)
            - Questionnaire July 1993 (Box 18)
            - Program Factsheet 1992 (Box 18)
          - University of Michigan Survey of Student Experiences in the College of Engineering
            - c07: Research Project/Honors Thesis Proposal and Evaluation 1993-1994 (Box 18)
            - Correspondence with the College of Engineering 1994 (Box 18)
            - Data Analysis and Coding (Carissa Bowles) undated (Box 18)
            - Findings (Carissa Bowles) January 1995 (Box 18)
            - Questionnaires September 1993, January 1994 (Box 18)
        - Internships (High School) 1988 (Box 43)
          [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2063 ]
        - Internships (Undergraduate) 1989/90 (Box 43)
          [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2065 ]
        - Research Surveys
          - Marian Sarah Parker Scholars (Engineering Pipeline Project) Completed Questionnaires April 1995 (Box 43)
            [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2070 ]
          - WISEWING Sophomore Women in Science and Engineering Residential Program Survey 1994 (Box 43)
          - WISEWING Non-Returning Women (Past Participants) undated (Box 43)
      - Women of Color Task Force 1989 (Box 18)
      - Women on Campus (Symposium, 10/14/1970)
        - Correspondence 1970-1971 (Box 18)
        - Drafts and Notes 1970 (Box 18)
        - Planning 1970 (Box 18)
      - Women's Career Fair Evaluations 1978-1979 (Box 18)
      - WING [Women's Initiative Group]
        - Correspondence 1986-1991, 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Minutes 1986-1990, 2 folders (Box 19)
        - Model Employer Task Force 1987-1989 (Box 19)
        - Reports and General 1981-1991, 4 folders (Box 19)
        - Retreats 1986-1987 (Box 19)
        - Task Forces and Subcommittees 1987-1989 (Box 19)
        - Women's Coalition Building 1988-1989 (Box 19)
      - Women's Network 1981-1982 (Box 19)
      - Women's Research and Education Institute 1981-1985 (Box 19)
      - Women's Studies Program 1972-1973 (Box 19)
      - Zonta 1965, 1990 (Box 19)
- Individual Staff Files 1919-1999
  The Individual Staff Files include the files of Barbara Anton, Ruth Bordin, Louise Gilbert Cain, Jean Campbell, Myra Fabian, Carol Hollenshead, Sue Kaufmann, Jean Manis, Hazel Markus, Dorothy McGuigan, Vivian Rogers, and Patricia Wulp. In addition to their commitment to advocacy for women through their positions and duties at CEW, center staff members have been deeply involved in their own professional fields. As such, the individual staff members' files contain a spectrum of materials ranging from official CEW business to quite personal material. For example, the files document individuals' duties at CEW (e.g. Myra Fabian's counseling files); university duties following from CEW work (e.g. Myra Fabian's WING files); non-CEW-related university work (e.g. Carol Hollenshead's files relating to her position at the Office for the Vice President of Research); professional papers (e.g. Myra Fabian's NAWDAC files); and personal papers (e.g. Vivian Rogers' Lumpectomy Support Group file). Some sets of papers fall into more than one category, for example Sue Kaufmann's Sexual Harassment Policies files, which document activities she began while at other University of Michigan units and continued once she came to CEW.
  - Barbara Anton 1978-1982
    (Founder). Louise Cain, although named director of the center in 1964, never acted in that capacity. She returned to the center in 1968 as Special Projects Director. Her files are useful for their coverage of some of CEW's early programs.
    - Career Decision Making 1978-1980 (Box 19)
    - Women's Career Fair 1979-1982, 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Ruth Bordin 1993-1999
    - A Dangerous Experiment Revision (Women at Michigan: 'The Dangerous Experiment', 1870s to the Present)
      (Also see Dorothy McGuigan files and topical photographs)
      - Preface Drafts 1993, undated (Box 19)
      - Chapters 1-7 Drafts 1993-1994, undated, 7 folders (Box 19)
      - CEW Oral Histories undated (Box 19)
      - Publicity 1999 (Box 19)
  - Louise Cain 1967-1974
    - Centennial of Women on Campus 1969-1970 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence 1968-1970 (Box 20)
    - Publicity and Publications 1969-1970 (Box 20)
    - Scholarships 1969-1970 (Box 20)
    - Speeches and notes 1967-1974 (Box 20)
    - Women on Campus Conference October 14, 1970 (Box 20)
  - Jean Campbell 1965-1985
    As director during the center's first twenty years, 1965-1985, Jean Campbell was involved in all aspects of CEW's activities. As a result of Campbell's central position, the bulk of her files from the early CEW accessions formed the core of the 'Topical Files' series. As more of her materials have been accessioned, an individual series was created for her that includes more personal, less central materials (such as her correspondence, speeches, and talks) and materials from the new accessions.
    - Academic Interlude Program 1977-1979 (Box 20)
    - Adult and Continuing Education Task Force 1977-1978 (Box 20)
    - Bush Program in Child Development conferences 1982-1984 (Box 20)
    - Catherine O'Brien Award 1978 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence 1965-1966, 1970-1985, undated (Box 20)
    - England (Education and Legislation concerning Women), ca 1969-1973 (Box 20)
    - Ford Foundation
      - Correspondence 1976-1981 (Box 20)
      - Ford-Funded Women's Research Centers 1974-1982 (Box 20)
      - General 1976-1977 (Box 20)
      - Grant Proposals and Reports 1977-1983 (Box 20)
    - Ford Motor Company Fund 1979 (Box 20)
    - Graduate School Tuition and Fees 1977-1978 (Box 20)
    - Haber Report on Extension and Adult Education 1970-1971 (Box 20)
    - International Interdisciplinary Congresses on Women 1981-1984 (Box 20)
      (includes Jean Campbell paper at Haifa conference: "The Integration of Service, Advocacy, and Research in a University Women's Center"; and Barbara Sloat paper at Groningen conference: "Women in Science: A University Program of Intervention, Outreach, and Research")
    - International Women's Year 1975-1976 (Box 20)
      ("Women and Educational Change", November 15-16, 1975 "The Role of Women in Conflict Resolution and Peace"; "Women and Work", April 3, 1976)
    - International Women's Year/Decade 1984 (Box 20)
    - LSA Commission on Graduation Requirements 1972 (Box 20)
    - Michigan State Planning Committee--ACE National Identification Program for the Advancement of Women in Higher Education 1978-1980 (Box 20)
    - Non-Traditional Student Survey, 1977- (Box 20)
    - Non-Traditional Student Survey--Proposal 1976 (Box 20)
    - Participant Follow-up Study (Publicity and Inquiries) 1972-1979 (Box 20)
    - Power Foundation 1970-1984 (Box 20)
    - Reports on UM Women 1977-1978 (Box 21)
    - Sample CEW Materials for Distribution (Binder), ca 1971-1982 (Box 21)
    - Scholarship Program History, ca 1968-1979 (Box 21)
    - Speeches and Talks, ca 1964-1982, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Suggestions for a Women's Agenda at UM 1978-1981 (Box 21)
    - Syllabi 1977, undated (Box 21)
      (Freedman and Gamson)
    - University of Mid-America Site Visit 1976 (Box 21)
    - Grievances 1978 (Box 43)
  - Myra Fabian 1966-1988
    The files of Myra Fabian (counselor, circa 1968-1988) are divided into records of her oversight of CEW's counseling function, her involvement with the leadership of the National Association of Women Deans, Administrators, and Counselors and its Michigan chapter, and miscellaneous topical files. The counseling files document the philosophy and implementation of developmental (as opposed to psychiatric) counseling at CEW. Fabian's topical files consist largely of her speaking engagements, which often took the form of either talks on CEW and its service, advocacy, and research functions or of workshops similar to CEW's group counseling workshops.
    - Counseling (Group Workshops)
      - Assertiveness Training, Fall 1976, Winter 1980 (Box 21)
      - Career Decision Making Workshops
        - "Approaching Your Career Decision" 1977 (Box 21)
        - "Career Decisions" 1978-1980 (Box 21)
        - Career Decision Making Group 1982 (Box 21)
        - "Career Decision-Making: The Step Before the Job Search" 1983, 1984, 1987, 3 folders (Box 21)
        - Miscellaneous Background Materials 1976-1985 (Box 21)
      - "Careers in Communications" 1981 (Box 21)
      - Counselor Training Workshop: "Designing Structured Group Experiences: A Workshop for Counselors" December 1978 (Box 21)
      - Decision Making 1979-1982 (Box 21)
      - Group Counseling Planning and Evaluation 1974-1985 (Box 21)
      - Job Hunt/Job Search Clubs
        - General 1984-1988, 4 folders (Box 21)
        - Interview Role-Play Materials 1984-1985 (Box 21)
        - Miscellaneous and Background materials, circa 1983-1988 (Box 21)
      - Mid-Life Women's Groups
        - "Woman in the Middle: Issues and Options at Mid-Life" 1979 (Box 21)
        - "Better than Ever: Options for Women in their Middle Years" 1981 (Box 21)
      - "Working Women: Making the Most of It" 1986 (Box 21)
    - Counseling (Individual)
      - Descriptions of Services 1974-1984 (Box 21)
      - Drop-In Scheduling and Reports 1973-1977 (Box 21)
      - Implications of Research on Women [for Counseling Services], ca 1972-1980 (Box 21)
      - Issues 1981-1982 (Box 22)
      - Miscellaneous Information 1966-1972 (Box 22)
      - Procedures and Orientation Material 1968, 1973-1983 (Box 22)
      - Procedures--Revisions 1966, 1971-1983 (Box 22)
      - Proposals 1970-1979 (Box 22)
      - Staff Development 1977, 1984-1986 (Box 22)
      - Staff Discussions, circa 1972-1979 (Box 22)
      - Sue Golden's Paper on CEW Counseling and other Resources, circa 1977-1981 (Box 22)
    - Counseling (Interns and Staff)
      - Assessment/Evaluation Aids, ca 1980-1984 (Box 22)
      - Interns 1974-1986 (Box 22)
      - Job Searches and Position Descriptions, ca 1979-1984 (Box 22)
    - NAWDAC/MAWDAC [National/Michigan Association for Women's Deans, Administrators, and Counselors]
      - MAWDAC 1977-1985, 2 folders (Box 22)
        (also see M. Fabian's 'Personal Activities' folder)
      - NAWDAC
        - 1984 Annual Conference
          - Executive Board Meeting 1984 (Box 22)
          - General 1984 (Box 22)
          - State Leaders Workshop 1984 (Box 22)
        - 1986 Annual Conference, 1986 (Box 22)
        - Association Relations 1983-1984 (Box 22)
        - CEW Pre-Conference Workshop 1978 (Box 22)
        - Continuing Education Section 1979-1981 (Box 22)
        - Executive Board 1983-1984 (Box 22)
        - Materials for Newly Elected Board Members 1983 (Box 22)
        - Miscellaneous/General 1971-1973, 1978, 1982-1987, 6 folders (Box 22)
        - Outgoing Presidential Correspondence (Binder) 1987 (Box 22)
        - Presidential Correspondence (Binder) 1986-1987 (Box 22)
        - Proposed 1984 Symposium, 1983-1984 (Box 23)
        - State Associations 1983-1984 (Box 23)
        - Strategic Planning (Binder) 1985-1986 (Box 23)
    - Topical
      - Alpha Xi Delta Panel May 10, 1972 (Box 23)
      - (American Association of University Women) presentations and workshops
        - Decision Making 1986 (Box 23)
        - "Leadership: Locus of Control" April 23, 1985 (Box 23)
        - Recent Graduates Speech 1971 (Box 23)
      - Arrow and work with Undergraduates 1970-1975, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Association of American Colleges (On Campus With Women) 1980 (Box 23)
        (Project on the status of women on campus)
      - CEW Executive Committee Briefs 1970-1971, 1980, 1984 (Box 23)
      - Chelsea Women's Group Presentation 1977-1978 (Box 23)
      - Commission for Women 1976-1977, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
      - Correspondence (Miscellaneous) 1970-1981, undated (Box 23)
      - Correspondence (Vivian Rogers) 1986-1988 (Box 23)
      - Day on Campus/Re-Entry Programs ("Re-Entry '77", '"Day on Campus" and "Re-Entry: A Day on Campus") 1977-1978 (Box 23)
      - Dual Careers Panel 1985-1986 (Box 23)
        (CEW, WIS, and LSA joint Program)
      - EB-APGA (European Branch-American Personnel and Guidance Association) Conference Workshop Proposal 1983 (Box 23)
      - Filing System undated (Box 23)
      - Graduate and Professional Admissions 1973-1980 (Box 23)
      - Graduate and Professional Program Planning 1984-1985 (Box 23)
        (including "Women's Lives in the Information Society")
      - Grass Lake Women's Evening Group (Presentation) 1975 (Box 23)
      - Interim Director Search 1980 (Box 23)
      - Michigan College Counselors Association (Speaking engagements) 1972-1973 (Box 23)
      - Michigan College Personnel Association (Older Students Workshop) 1978 (Box 23)
      - Michigan Women's Studies Association--Conference May 3-4, 1974 (Box 23)
      - Michigan Women's Studies Association--Pre-Conference Workshop April 1982 (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous Speeches 1966-1977 and circa 1970s, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - National Coalition Study of Continuing Education Programs for Women 1974 (Box 23)
      - Older Students 1977 (Box 23)
      - Personal Activities 1974-1984, undated (Box 23)
      - Programs 1976 (Box 23)
      - Research Series in Adult Development 1983-1985 (Box 23)
      - "Saving a Women's Center", circa 1983 (Box 23)
        (Also see Core Administrative files on 1982 CEW review)
      - Scholarship Awards Night (April 21, 1981) 1980-1981 (Box 23)
      - School of Social Work Contacts 1984 (Box 23)
      - School of Social Work Field Instructors' Course 1985 (Box 23)
      - Sink Alumnae Group Presentation [On women in their middle years] November 1981 (Box 23)
      - Speaker Requests 1971-1977 (Box 23)
      - Surviving and Thriving in Graduate and Professional School (2/5/1983) 1982-1983 (Box 23)
      - Surviving and Thriving in Graduate and Professional School (Contact People) 1982-1983 (Box 23)
      - UM Children's Center Mothers' Group May 10, 1982 (Box 23)
      - UM Dearborn "Careers in Science" conference March 27, 1982 (Box 23)
      - "Women in Communications" Speech December 1983 (Box 23)
      - WING Women's Center Task Force 1987-1988, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Women's Life Cycle and Public Policy Conference November 7-8, 1979 (Box 24)
      - Women's Planning Retreat 1986-1987 (Box 24)
        (also see WING Women's Center Task Force records)
    - Counseling (Individual)
      - Notes 1975-1983, undated (Box 43)
    - Counseling (Interns and Staff)
      - Former Interns 1981, 1984-1985 (Box 43)
      - Intern Files 1978-1985, 8 folders (Box 43)
      - Potential Interns 1976-1977, 1980-1982 (Box 43)
        [SR RESTRICTED until January 1 2057 ]
  - Carol Hollenshead
    Carol Hollenshead's files (Director, 1988-present) include detailed records of the planning and execution of the CURIES conference on Women in Science, Mathematics, and Engineering (sponsored by grants from the Sloan Foundation), including the follow-up publications and policy recommendations that came out of the conference. Another major subseries within Hollenshead's papers documents her research at the Institute of Gerontology on older women and work. The bulk of these files consists of drafts and revisions of Hollenshead's research papers. Other highlights include files from Hollenshead's role on the executive committee for the Michigan Initiative on Women's Health and the 1994 CEW faculty survey.
    - 1972-1998
      - CEW Faculty Survey
        - Advisory Board 1994 (Box 24)
        - Draft for Beth Reed 1994 (Box 24)
        - Other Institutions 1993-1994, undated (Box 24)
        - Proposals and Drafts 1994 (Box 24)
        - Questionnaire undated (Box 24)
      - Committee on a Multicultural University (COMU) 1992-1994 (Box 24)
        (Also see the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs record group)
      - CURIES / Sloan Conference on Women in Science, Mathematics, and Engineering
        - Advisory Committee
          - Correspondence 1993-1994 (Box 24)
          - Member Lists undated (Box 24)
          - Planning Meeting
            - Agenda and Handouts, July 15 1993 (Box 24)
            - Planning and Correspondence 1993 (Box 24)
            - Carol Hollenshead Notes 1993 (Box 24)
            - Summary and Follow-up 1993 (Box 24)
        - Authors' Meeting, June 21 1994 (Box 24)
        - Budget 1993 (Box 24)
        - Conference
          - Description undated (Box 24)
          - Evaluations (Planning) 1994 (Box 24)
          - Evaluations (Completed) 1994 (Box 24)
          - Folder May 1994 (Box 24)
          - Invitations October 1993-March 1994 (Box 24)
          - Invitation Follow-ups March-May 1994 (Box 24)
          - Notes and Recordings May 1994 (Box 24)
          - Paper Outlines March-April 1994 (Box 24)
          - Participant Lists 1994-1995, undated (Box 24)
          - Participant Photographs May 1994 (Box 24)
          - Planning Notes 1993-1994 (Box 24)
          - Schedule May 1994 (Box 24)
        - Correspondence July 1993-1995 (Box 24)
        - Correspondence (Background) 1991-February 1993 (Box 24)
        - CURIES Descriptions 1993, undated (Box 25)
        - CURIES Stationery 1993, undated (Box 25)
        - The Equity Agenda
          - Authors' Recommendations undated (Box 25)
          - Carol Hollenshead Presentation to the Sloan Foundation August 8, 1994 (Box 25)
          - Drafts July 1994-June 1995 (Box 25)
          - Pre-Readers' Letters and Draft April-May 1995 (Box 25)
          - Pre-Readers' Recommendations August-September 1995 (Box 25)
        - The Equity Agenda / The Equity Equation--Publication and Dissemination, 1996 (Box 25)
          (includes disks)
        - The Equity Agenda / The Equity Equation--Publication Mailing Lists, 1996, undated (Box 25)
        - The Equity Equation
          - Publisher Information (Not Jossey-Bass) July 1994-January 1995 (Box 25)
          - Publisher (Jossey-Bass) September 1994-June 1995 (Box 25)
        - Grant Proposals
          - Accepted Proposal and Extensions September 1993-April 1995 (Box 25)
          - CURIES Planning Grant April-June 1993 (Box 25)
          - New Sloan Proposal on Women Graduate Students in Science and Engineering December 1994 (Box 25)
          - Post-Conference Publication Proposal August 1994 (Box 25)
          - Preliminary NACME/CURIES Joint Proposal January-April 1993 (Box 25)
        - Hollenshead Conference Paper
          - Background Material and Correspondence December 1993-April 1994 (Box 25)
          - Drafts and Revisions May-October 1994 (Box 25)
          - Overheads May 1994 (Box 25)
        - NACME Forum Conference June 3, 1994 (Box 25)
          (Presentation of CURIES findings)
        - Sloan Foundation 1992-1996, 2 folders (Box 25)
        - Pinn Conference Paper June 1994 (Box 25)
      - Dreyfus Foundation Project on Student Success (Chemistry Focus Groups) 1992-1994 (Box 25)
      - Institute of Gerontology
        (also see IOG Collection)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Administration 1980-1983, undated (Box 25)
          - Center for Women Policy Studies 1981 (Box 25)
          - Correspondence 1973-1983 (Box 25)
          - Women and Aging Syllabus 1988 (Box 25)
          - Women's Law Fund Deposition 1982-1983 (Box 25)
        - Research Articles, Studies, and Presentations
          - Aging, Work, and Employment conference, Akron OH September 22-23, 1981 (Box 25)
          - AARP/National Council on the Aging conference April-May 1986 (Box 25)
          - Audiovisual Reviews for The Gerontologist, 1979 (Box 25)
          - "Behind the Myths: A Demographic Profile of the Elderly", Carol Hollenshead and Jeanne Miller 1984 (Box 25)
          - "Displaced Homemakers: Health Status, Health Insurance, and Access to Health Services", Displaced Homemakers Network, November 20 1985 (Box 25)
          - "Fictional Portrayals of Family Dynamics: Older Women Compared to Older Men", Ruth Spencer and Carol Hollenshead 1980 (Box 25)
          - Governor's Conference on Aging, Flint MI September 15-17, 1986 (Box 25)
          - Grantsmanship speeches and workshops 1979-1984 (Box 26)
          - "Group Work with the De-Institutionalized Elderly", Berit Ingersoll and Carol Hollenshead 1978-1982 (Box 26)
          - "The Human Science Research Paradigm: Underlying Assumptions", Carol Hollenshead 1982, 1985 (Box 26)
          - Michigan White House Conference on Aging 1980-1981 (Box 26)
          - Miscellaneous speeches and conferences 1977-1983 (Box 26)
          - "Old at 40: Women in the Workplace", Institute of Gerontology 1984 (Box 26)
          - "The Older Woman in America", Carol Hollenshead 1980 (Box 26)
          - Older Women and Work--EMU Workshop 1987 (Box 26)
          - Older Women and Work NCOA [National Council on Aging] Speech Notes March 1983 (Box 26)
          - Older Women and Work Speeches April 1986, undated (Box 26)
          - "Older Women at Work", Carol Hollenshead January-July 1982 (Box 26)
          - Older Women in Ads--Carol Hollenshead and Berit Ingersoll article versions with title changes 1978-1983 (Box 26)
            ("Older Women: A Study of Print Ads", "Aging Women: A Study of Print Advertisements", and "Middle-Aged and Older Women in Print Advertisements")